<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.fabio.SayWrite</id>
  <name>SayWrite</name>
  <summary>Speak naturally, get clean text anywhere</summary>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>MIT</project_license>
  <developer_name>Fabio</developer_name>
  <description>
    <p>
      SayWrite turns your voice into polished text. Press a shortcut, speak
      naturally, and your words land — cleaned up and ready to use — wherever
      you're typing.
    </p>
    <p>
      Runs entirely on your machine by default. No account needed, no data
      leaves your computer. Optionally connect a cloud API for faster results
      on older hardware.
    </p>
    <p>
      This release supports GNOME on Wayland. Direct text insertion uses the
      IBus input method bridge and has been validated on GNOME Wayland setups.
      On other desktops, SayWrite falls back to clipboard delivery automatically
      and reports which mode is active so you always know what to expect.
    </p>
  </description>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.fabio.SayWrite.desktop</launchable>
  <provides>
    <binary>saywrite</binary>
  </provides>
  <categories>
    <category>Utility</category>
    <category>AudioVideo</category>
    <category>Office</category>
  </categories>
  <recommends>
    <display_length compare="ge">480</display_length>
  </recommends>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />
  <releases>
    <release version="0.3.4" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Click-to-dictate button for users without a working hotkey.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Main window's dictation button is now clickable to start and stop dictation, so users on desktops where the GNOME shortcut fallback can't be installed still have a working path to dictation with clipboard delivery</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.3" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Dictation hotkey now works out of the box.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Onboarding completion is tied to the installed Flatpak commit, so reinstalling or upgrading re-runs onboarding</li>
          <li>Hands-free GNOME shortcut self-heals on every launch when the GlobalShortcuts portal is unavailable — installs or repairs the custom keybinding automatically so users don't have to run any setup script</li>
          <li>Shortcut command path now points to the host-deployed launcher (~/.local/bin/saywrite-dictation.sh) instead of the dev-only repo path, so the hotkey fires for Flatpak users</li>
          <li>Fixed the launcher script silently no-op'ing on the removed state-marker file</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.2" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Removes host daemon launch deadlock.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>saywrite-host no longer gates its startup on the app's D-Bus name being owned, which could deadlock when the host was D-Bus-auto-activated during GApplication registration (fixes "refusing to start because SayWrite is not running" + register timeout)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.1" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Startup reliability fix.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Host daemon start no longer blocks the GTK main loop, so repeated launches don't pile up as orphaned processes and time out with "Failed to register"</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.0" date="2026-04-19">
      <description>
        <p>Reliability fix for Direct Typing on fresh Flatpak installs.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Host companion now uses D-Bus name ownership to detect the app, fixing a PID-namespace mismatch that left the daemon "active but unreachable" after install on Flatpak</li>
          <li>Settings surfaces host daemon journal output when install succeeds but the daemon can't be reached, so failures explain themselves</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.2.0" date="2026-04-11">
      <description>
        <p>First supported release targeting GNOME Wayland.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Global hotkey dictation via host companion daemon</li>
          <li>Direct text insertion via IBus on GNOME Wayland</li>
          <li>Local transcription with whisper.cpp (no cloud required)</li>
          <li>Optional cloud transcription via OpenAI-compatible API</li>
          <li>In-app host companion installation</li>
          <li>Animated waveform during listening, inline setup actions, insertion mode indicator</li>
          <li>Clipboard and notification fallback when direct typing is unavailable</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
